Guide to the Nina Rosenblum Papers MSS.558
Fales Library and Special Collections
Nina Rosenblum Papers
1868-2018
1974-2014
Fales Library and Special Collections
Rosenblum, Nina
MSS.558
40.2 Linear Feet in 27 manuscript boxes, 15 record cartons, 3 small flat boxes, 1 medium flat box, 6 cassette boxes, 1 LP box, 2 card boxes, 1 small box, 1 oversized custom box, 1 shared tall LP box, 1 shared CD box, 5 film cans, 2 upright video containers, 3 flat file folders, 1 shared manuscript box, and 5 folders in 2 shared oversized flat boxes
562 Gigabytes in 3562 computer files
23 16mm_film_reels
112 VHS
16 U-matic
7 Betacam
55 audiocassettes
385 MiniDV
14 DAT
4 Hi8
2 DVCPRO
1 VHS-C
41 Quarter_Inch_Audio_Reel
2 1_Inch_Video_Reel
2 2_Inch_Videoreel
117 Betacam_SP
2 D-2
54 Digital_Betacam
15 DVCAM
1 Super_8mm_Film_Reel
Nina Rosenblum (1950- ) is a documentary film and television director, writer, and producer. She is the founder of Daedalus Productions, Inc. with Daniel V. Allentuck, and a member of the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences, the Directors Guild of America, and New York Women in Film and Television. Rosenblum has taught documentary film production at various universities, including New York University and Columbia University. Through her documentary work, Rosenblum addresses topics such as the history of photography, the role of documentary film in a larger social context, and human rights. This collection consists of materials created and collected by Nina Rosenblum documenting her career as a documentary film producer and director. Materials in this collection include negatives, master prints, and sound prints in analog and digital format of Rosenblum's various films, as well as documentation for these projects, such as correspondence, research files, production scrapbooks, calendars, posters, and reviews. Works by Rosenblum represented in this collection include America and Lewis Hine (1984), Through the Wire (1990), Liberators: Fighting on Two Fronts in World War II (1992), Lock-Up: The Prisoners of Rikers Island (1994), Walter Rosenblum: In Search of Pitt Street (1999), Code Yellow: Hospital at Ground Zero (2002), and Ordinary Miracles: The Photo League's New York (2012). This collection also contains materials concerning her parents, photographer Walter Rosenblum and photographic historian Naomi Rosenblum, including photographs by Walter Rosenblum and items related to A History of Women Photographers (1996), a book by Naomi Rosenblum. Additionally, there are some personal photographs, award certificates, samples of Rosenblum's artwork prior to her career as a filmmaker, and a teaching portfolio.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Nina Rosenblum in November 2018, December 2021, and February 2024; the accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2018.116, 2021.041, and 2024.017.
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged into 20 series, 15 of which have been further arranged into subseries. The series and subseries arrangement is as follows:
Series I. Personal
Subseries I.A. Nina Rosenblum
Subseries I.B. Naomi Rosenblum
Subseries I.C. Walter Rosenblum
Series II. Artwork and Teaching
Subseries II.A. Artwork
Subseries II.B. Teaching
Series III. Events and Press
Series IV. America and Lewis Hine
Subseries IV.A. Administrative Materials
Subseries IV.B. Awards and Honors
Subseries IV.C. Marketing Materials
Subseries IV.D. Press
Subseries IV.E. Production Materials
Subseries IV.F. Research Materials
Subseries IV.G. Screenings and Festivals
Series V. Through the Wire
Subseries V.A. Marketing Materials
Subseries V.B. Press and Awards
Subseries V.C. Production Materials
Subseries V.D. Screenings and Festivals
Series VI. Liberators: Fighting on Two Fronts in WWII
Subseries VI.A. Awards and Honors
Subseries VI.B. Controversy
Subseries VI.C. Marketing Materials
Subseries VI.D. Press and Reviews
Subseries VI.E. Production Materials
Subseries VI.F. Research Materials
Subseries VI.G. Screenings and Festivals
Series VII. The Untold West: The Black West
Subseries VII.A Administrative Materials
Subseries VII.B Press and Awards
Subseries VII.C Production Materials
Subseries VII.D Research Materials
Subseries VII.E Screenings and Festivals
Series VIII. Lock-Up: The Prisoners of Rikers Island and Beat Down: The Case of Raymond Alvarez
Subseries VIII.A. Lock-Up
Subseries VIII.B. Beat Down
Series IX. Slave Ship: The Testimony of the Henrietta Marie
Series X. A History of Women Photographers
Series XI. Walter Rosenblum: In Search of Pitt Street
Subseries XI.A. Correspondence
Subseries XI.B. Marketing Materials
Subseries XI.C. Press and Awards
Subseries XI.D. Production Materials
Subseries XI.E. Screenings and Festivals
Series XII. Sly and Jimi: The Skin I'm In
Subseries XII.A. Correspondence
Subseries XII.B. Marketing Materials
Subseries XII.C. Production Materials
Series XIII. Unintended Consequences
Subseries XIII.A. In Arm's Reach
Subseries XIII.B. Marketing Materials, Honors, and Press
Subseries XIII.C. Production Materials
Subseries XIII.D. Research Materials
Series XIV. Code Yellow: Hospital at Ground Zero
Subseries XIV.A. Marketing Materials and Screenings
Subseries XIV.B. Production Materials
Series XV. An Empty Place at the Table
Series XVI. Zahira's Peace
Subseries XVI.A. Administrative Materials
Subseries XVI.B. Marketing Materials
Subseries XVI.C. Press and Awards
Subseries XVI.D. Production Materials
Subseries XVI.E. Screenings and Festivals
Series XVII. Twin Lenses
Subseries XVII.A. Administrative Materials
Subseries XVII.B. Marketing Materials
Subseries XVII.C. Press and Reviews
Subseries XVII.D. Production Materials
Subseries XVII.E. Screenings and Festivals
Series XVIII. In the Name of Democracy
Subseries XVIII.A. Administrative Materials
Subseries XVIII.B. Marketing Materials
Subseries XVII.C. Production Materials
Subseries XVII.D. Screenings, Festivals, and Press
Series XIX. Ordinary Miracles: The Photo League's New York
Subseries XIX.A. Administrative Materials
Subseries XIX.B. Marketing Materials
Subseries XIX.C. Press and Reviews
Subseries XIX.D. Production Materials
Subseries XIX.E. Research Materials
Subseries XIX.F. Screenings and Festivals
Series XX. Unrealized Projects and Tributes
Biographical Note
Nina Rosenblum (1950- ) is a documentary film and television director, writer, and producer. She is the founder of Daedalus Productions, Inc. with Daniel V. Allentuck, and a member of the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences, the Directors Guild of America, and New York Women in Film and Television. Rosenblum has taught documentary film production at various universities, including New York University and Columbia University. Through her documentary work, Rosenblum addresses topics such as the history of photography, the role of documentary film in a larger social context, and human rights issues, such as prison reform. Rosenblum's works include America and Lewis Hine (1984), Through the Wire (1990), Liberators: Fighting on Two Fronts in World War II (1992), Lock-Up: The Prisoners of Rikers Island (1994), Walter Rosenblum: In Search of Pitt Street (1999), Code Yellow: Hospital at Ground Zero (2002), and Ordinary Miracles: The Photo League's New York (2012). Rosenblum received a 1994 Emmy Award for The Untold West: The Black West (1993) and an Academy Award nomination for Best Feature Documentary for Liberators.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Some audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Fales Library and Special Collections (special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596) with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of materials created and collected by Nina Rosenblum documenting her career as a documentary film producer and director on subjects including prison reform, women photographers, and the Photo League. Materials in this collection include negatives, film elements (such as voiceovers, interviews, credits, and trailers) on various media, master prints, and sound prints in analog and digital format of Rosenblum's various films. Also included is documentation for these projects, such as correspondence, research files, production scrapbooks, calendars, contracts, posters, budgets, press releases, photographs at openings and film festivals, and published reviews. Works by Rosenblum represented in this collection include America and Lewis Hine (1984), Through the Wire (1990), Liberators: Fighting on Two Fronts in World War II (1992), Lock-Up: The Prisoners of Rikers Island (1994), Walter Rosenblum: In Search of Pitt Street (1999), Code Yellow: Hospital at Ground Zero (2002), and Ordinary Miracles: The Photo League's New York (2012). This collection also contains materials concerning her parents, photographer Walter Rosenblum and photographic historian Naomi Rosenblum, including photographs by Walter Rosenblum and items related to A History of Women Photographers (1996), a book by Naomi Rosenblum. Additionally, there are some personal photographs, award certificates, samples of Rosenblum's artwork prior to her career as a filmmaker, and a teaching portfolio.
Appraisal
Off-air recordings, in both analog and digital formats, have been appraised out of the collection due to copyright limitations. These recordings include YouTube Clips, any recording from a copyrighted broadcast or cable television transmission, and local television recordings. Broadcast recordings of which Nina Rosenblum was a producer, director, or co-producer have been retained.
Related Materials
For more information about Naomi and Walter Rosenblum, see the Walter and Naomi Rosenblum Collection of Photography and Photographic History (MSS 556), also at Fales Library and Special Collections.
Documentary films -- United States.; Documentary films -- History and criticism; Women motion picture producers and directors -- United States.; Motion picture producers and directors.; Human rights.; Prisoners -- Civil rights -- United States.; Rosenblum, Nina; Daedalus Productions; Photo League; Rosenblum, Naomi; Rosenblum, Walter, 1919-2006
- Series I. Personal, 1946-2018; 3.48 Linear Feet in 3 manuscript boxes and 2 record cartons; 2 U-matic; 2 VHS; 76.92 Gigabytes in 681 computer files
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of biographical materials on Nina Rosenblum such as family and personal photographs, personal correspondence, and daily planners. There are materials related to Rosenblum's parents, Naomi and Walter Rosenblum, including video recordings of lectures and award ceremonies, writing samples, correspondence, photographs, recorded interviews, interview transcripts, and an oral history transcript. More recent exhibition materials (2005-2018), such as correspondence, video recordings, and installation photographs, of Walter Rosenblum's work are included. These materials reflect the influence that her parents' work had on Rosenblum's work. Also included are materials created by Rosenblum's husband and frequent collaborator, Daniel Allentuck, such as a journal and video demo. Recordings of memorial services, possibly of friends or family members, are included as well. This series also contains materials related to the Rosenblum Photo Archive (now, the Rosenblum Photography Collection), overseen by Naomi and Nina Rosenblum. The archive includes works by Walter Rosenblum, Paul Strand, and others. Materials related to the Rosenblum Photo Archive, all electronic, include correspondence, proposals from auction houses, and lists of exhibited works.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically into three subseries, with Nina Rosenblum first.
  - Subseries I.A. Nina Rosenblum, 1967-2018; 2.40 Linear Feet in 3 manuscript boxes and 1 record carton; 1 U-matic; 1 VHS; 6.52 Gigabytes in 178 computer files
    This subseries consists of biographical and personal materials of Nina Rosenblum. Materials include correspondence; photographs; daily planners; materials from her husband, Daniel Allentuck; video remembrances; and notes.
    - Address Book, circa 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Biographical Material, 1967-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Blanche's Memorial, 2002 (Box 46, Vhs 558.0280)
    - Correspondence, 1967-2006
      - Electronic Records, FA_MSS_558_ER_1
      - Letters and Email Printouts (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Daily Planners, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Daily Planners, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Daily Planners, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Daily Planners, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Daily Planners, 2005-2006 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Daniel Allentuck, 1979-2000
      - Journal and Writing, 1994-2000 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - "Their Life's Sweat" -- Demo, October 30, 1979 (Box 24, U-matic 558.0568)
    - Negatives, circa 1980-2000 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Photographs, 1980-2000
      - Electronic Records, FA_MSS_558_ER_2
      - Prints (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Rosenblum Photo Archive, 1999-2018; FA_MSS_558_ER_3
    - Slides, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Video Recording -- "Remembrance of Les", 2011; FA_MSS_558_ER_122
  - Subseries I.B. Naomi Rosenblum, 1950-2018; 0.44 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box; 49.13 Gigabytes in 340 computer files
    This subseries consists of personal and biographical materials of Naomi Rosenblum, Nina Rosenblum's mother. Materials include photographs, correspondence, writing samples, a video recording of a lecture, and press clippings.
    - Awards, 1998-2018; FA_MSS_558_ER_4
    - Biographical Material, 1999-2003; FA_MSS_558_ER_5
    - Correspondence, 2006-2011
      - Electronic Records, FA_MSS_558_ER_6
      - Letters and Emails (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Lecture -- Madrid, 2010; FA_MSS_558_ER_7
    - Photographs, circa 1950-2018; FA_MSS_558_ER_8
    - Press, 1994-1996
      - Clippings and Articles (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Electronic Records, FA_MSS_558_ER_9
    - Writing, 1986-2007; FA_MSS_558_ER_10
    - Video Recording -- Book Signing -- Rizzoli Cut, 2011; FA_MSS_558_ER_120
  - Subseries I.C. Walter Rosenblum, 1940-2018; 4.77 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box and 4 record cartons; 5 Betacam_SP; 7 Digital_Betacam; 4 VHS; 1 U-matic; 21.21 Gigabytes in 163 computer files
    This subseries contains personal and biographical materials of Walter Rosenblum, Nina Rosenblum's father. Materials include correspondence, writing samples, photographs, clippings, and interviews.
    - Awards, 1998-2004
      - Electronic Records -- Photographs, 1998; FA_MSS_558_ER_11
      - International Center of Photography -- 14th Annual Infinity Awards, 1998
        - Tape 1017, circa 1998 (Box 27, Betacam sp 558.0126)
        - Tape 1018, circa 1998 (Box 27, Betacam sp 558.0169)
        - Tape 1020, circa 1998 (Box 27, Betacam sp 558.0170)
        - Tape 1022, circa 1998 (Box 27, Betacam sp 558.0171)
        - Video Recording, May 4, 1998 (Box 26, Digital betacam 558.0876)
        - Video Recording, May 4, 1998 (Box 26, Digital betacam 558.0877)
        - Video Recording, May 4, 1998 (Box 26, Digital betacam 558.0878)
        - Video Recording, May 4, 1998 (Box 26, Digital betacam 558.0879)
        - Video Recording, May 4, 1998 (Box 26, Digital betacam 558.0880)
        - Video Recording, May 4, 1998 (Box 26, Digital betacam 558.0881)
        - Video Recording, May 4, 1998 (Box 26, Digital betacam 558.0885)
        - Video Recording, July 30, 1998 (Box 24, Betacam sp 558.0564)
        - Video Recording, August 7, 1998 (Box 28, Vhs 558.0590)
        - Video Recording, circa 1998 (Box 28, Vhs 558.0587)
        - Video Recording, circa 1998 (Box 28, Vhs 558.0597)
      - Video Recording -- Award Ceremony -- Spilimbergo -- Italian and English, 2004; FA_MSS_558_ER_121
    - "Bronx Issues and Answers" -- Peter J. Negroni Interviews Walter Rosenblum, undated (Box 24, U-matic 558.0565)
    - Correspondence and Biographical Material
      - Biographical Material -- Electronic Records, 2003-2008; FA_MSS_558_ER_12
      - Correspondence -- Electronic Records, 2002-2003; FA_MSS_558_ER_13
      - Letters and Biographies, 1946-2006 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Exhibitions, 2005-2018; FA_MSS_558_ER_14
    - Interview Transcripts
      - Electronic Records, 1998-2003; FA_MSS_558_ER_15
      - Paper Transcript, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Memorial
      - Electronic Records, 2006; FA_MSS_558_ER_16
      - Video Recording, March 21, 2006 (Box 27, Vhs 558.0256)
    - Oral History, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Photographs, circa early 1940s-2006; FA_MSS_558_ER_17
    - Press, 1987-2011
      - Clippings and Articles (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Electronic Records, FA_MSS_558_ER_18
    - Video Recording -- Walter Rosenblum and Paul Strand Friendship, 2010; FA_MSS_558_ER_127
    - Writing
      - Electronic Records, 2003; FA_MSS_558_ER_19
      - Manuscripts, 1977 and undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series II. Artwork and Teaching, 1969-2012; 2.76 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes, 1 small flat box, 1 medium flat box, 2 flat file folders, and 1 folder in a shared oversized box; 313 Megabytes in 4 computer files
  This series contains materials from Rosenblum's career as an artist and art professor, prior to her filmmaking career. Materials related to her art include exhibition catalogs, price lists, slides, negatives, awards, and press. Materials related to her teaching career consist of a teaching portfolio, correspondence, and event posters. At Union College, where Rosenblum taught, she also ran the art gallery, and those materials, such as exhibition postcards and catalogs, are included. Rosenblum discusses her artwork in a video included in the electronic records, providing insight into the topics that interested her and connections with her documentary work.
  Arranged alphabetically into two subseries, chronologically within each one.
  - Subseries II.A. Artwork, 1969-2004; 2.5 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes, 1 small flat box, and 1 large flat box; 313 Megabytes in 4 computer files
    This subseries includes samples of Rosenblum's artwork, exhibition materials, and a video recording of her talking about her paintings.
    - Sketches, undated (Box 2, Folder 6, Box Shared Fales 116, Folder 4)
    - Photographs, circa 1969-1981 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
    - Negatives, circa 1969-1981 (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
    - Slides, 1969-1981 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Electronic Records -- Paintings, Press, and Interview, 1972-2004; FA_MSS_558_ER_20
    - Press, Exhibition Postcards, Correspondence, and Price Lists, circa 1974-1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Exhibition Catalog, 1979 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Subseries II.B. Teaching, 1975-2012; .70 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box, 1 medium flat box, and 2 oversized folders
    This subseries consists of materials from Rosenblum's teaching career, most of which occurred at Union College. Materials include exhibition catalogs and announcements for the art gallery at Union College, correspondence, slides, and workshop schedules.
    - Union College and Union Gallery
      - Press, Gallery Exhibition Postcards and Catalogs, and Correspondence, 1975-1979 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Union Gallery Exhibition Posters, circa 1975-1979 (Flat-file-folder 9 left, Flat-file-folder 8 Left)
      - Campus Newspaper, 1978 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Other Universities, Workshops, and Symposia, 1984-2012 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Teaching Materials -- Slides, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Series III. Events and Press, 1984-2018; 4.53 Linear Feet in 3 manuscript boxes, 1 medium flat box, 1 cassette box, 3 record cartons, and 1 flat file folder; 2 VHS; 2 audiocassette; 1 Betacam_SP; 15.5 Gigabytes in 180 computer files
  This series contains materials related to events in which Rosenblum participated, such as film festivals and exhibitions. Many of these events celebrated Rosenblum's oeuvre, and not a specific film, so they are included here. Also included is any press on Rosenblum as a director, producer, writer, or her career in general, and membership materials to various organizations, such as the Directors Guild of America. These materials, especially related to career retrospectives, illustrate the important contributions that Rosenblum has made, in terms of gender and subject matter, to the documentary film industry.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Film Festivals
    - Electronic Records -- Photographs, Poster, and Video Recording, 2007-2018; FA_MSS_558_ER_21
    - General Participation and Attendance, 1984-2009 (Box 3, Folder 9, Box 4, Folder 1)
    - "Reel World" -- Clip Reel -- Tribeca Film Center -- Writer/Producer Cookie Carosella, undated (Box 38, Vhs 558.0186)
    - Retrospectives and Jury Participation -- Programs, Press, and Correspondence, 1999-2012 (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
    - Restrospectives -- Posters, 1999-2013 (Box 21, Folder 2, Flat-file-folder 8 Left)
  - Interviews
    - Electronic Records, 2004-2018; FA_MSS_558_ER_22
    - Institute for Research on Women and Gender -- Interview with Nina Rosenblum, undated (Box 28, Vhs 558.0586)
    - Nina with Peter Neufeld, undated (Box 62, Audiocassette 558.0228)
  - Press and Publicity on Rosenblum
    - Articles and Clippings, 1986-2013 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Electronic Records, 2004-2018; FA_MSS_558_ER_23
  - Professional Organizations -- Memberships and Participation, circa 1986-2013 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Professional Photographs, circa 1999
    - Electronic Records, FA_MSS_558_ER_24
    - Prints (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Women in Film Keynote -- Clip Reel, June 16, 1994 (Box 25, Betacam sp 558.0110)
- Series IV. America and Lewis Hine, 1868-2014; 6.26 Linear Feet in 3 manuscript boxes, 1 small flat box, 1 flat file folder, 4 record cartons, 1 film can, and 1 folder in a shared oversized box; 3 VHS; 2 U-matic; 1 16mm_film_reels; 8.78 Gigabytes in 33 computer files
  This series contains materials related to the feature documentary of the life and work of the social documentary photographer Lewis Wickes Hine, released in 1984. Materials relate to the production, marketing, and screening of the film. Such materials include posters, photographs (both electronic and print), film elements on various media, press and publicity, electronic film clips, and scrapbooks.
  Arranged alphabetically into seven subseries and alphanumerically within each one.
  - Subseries IV.A. Administrative Materials, 1980-2014; .44 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box
    This subseries consists of office records, such as correspondence and grant reports.
    - Correspondence, 1980-2014 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Grant Applications and Reports, 1980-1984 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Subseries IV.B. Awards and Honors, 1984-1986; .73 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box and 1 small flat box; 7.86 Megabytes in 4 computer files
    This subseries contains materials related to awards won by the film and filmmakers, which include correspondence, certificates, and programs.
    - Correspondence, Programs, and Certificates, 1984-1986 (Box 5, Folder 9, Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Photographs, circa 1986; FA_MSS_558_ER_25
  - Subseries IV.C. Marketing Materials, 1984-2014; .63 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box and 1 large flat box; 27.8 Megabytes in 3 computer files